Guide to the Samuel Waldron Lambert Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Waldron Lambert papers
1821-1939
1923-1939
MS 939
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
Chiefly correspondence relating to Lambert's activities concerning the Volstead Act and the Prohibition Amendment. Among his correspondents are Senator Hiram Bingham, Benjamin N. Cardozo, and Dr. Robert Lewis. Speeches, writings, newspaper clippings, and printed matter are also included in the papers. Other papers relate to research on scarlet fever and other medical subjects. Reflecting Lambert's book-collecting hobby are letters from the Bibliophile Society, the Grolier Club, and a letter dated 1821 to Mme. Eliza Bowen Jumel presented to Lambert as a gift. Also in the papers is the autograph album of Samuel W. Lambert, Jr. (Yale University, Class of 1919).
Lambert, Samuel W. (Samuel Waldron), 1859-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Samuel W. Lambert, 1943.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of letters and papers, 1821-1939, relating mainly to Dr. Samuel Waldron Lambert, Sr. The earliest item is a letter in French to Mme. Eliza (Bowen) Jumel signed Adele and endorsed De cubieres, written probably in 1821, presented to Lambert by W. L. Hardin. The next item is a letter of 1862 from Horace Greeley introducing J. H. Lambert. With the exception of a few items pertainig to Samuel W. Lambert, Jr., such as his autograph album, the remainder of the collection relates to Samuel W. Lambert, Sr.
Making up the bulk of the correspondence are letters and telegrams, 1932 and undated, to lambert from Senator Hiram Bingham relating to attempts to modify the Volstead Act, and letters from others, 1923-1932, concerning prohibition and the medical use of alcohol. Corresponents include the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, Benjamin N. Cardoza and Dr. Robert lewis; there are also papers on the Hastings medical liquor bill in the New York State Senate, accompanied by a letter from Dr. Harold Rypins to Dr. Linsly W. Williams, April 13, 1931. Other materials of Lamort's on rohibition and liquor (two small notebooks, loose notes, speeches and other writings, newpaper clippings and printed matter) are also included in this collection.
Other items in the correspondence include a letter from lambert to Dr. Samuel C. G. Watkins on recent research on scarlet fever, enclosing a leaflet about the lilly Company's new Scarlet Fever Streptococcus Antitoxin (1925); areport by Dr. E. M. Bluestone to the Public Health Relations committee of the New York Academy on the establishemnt of a hospital for chronic patients on Welfare Island(1934); a reprint of Dr. Smith Ely Jellifes' Aesculapius and Lzaak Walton, with notes by lampert on Walton and Charles Cotton (1993); Henry Osborn Taylor's memorial to his wife, "Julia Isham taylor," with accompanying letters (1934); Lambert's annotated copy of the Milbank Fund Quarterly (1934); letters from the Bibliophile society (1901-1915) and the Grolier Club, including one each from Bliss Perry (1926) and Henry T. Peters (1928); and a letter from Edward S. Dana (1879).
Also in the collection are several miscellaneous items such as bills, recipts, and assorted printed matter.
Yale University acquired these papers by a gift from the estate of Samuel W. Lambert in 1943.
Book collectors; Medicine; Prohibition; Scarlatina; Autographs (manuscripts); Physicians; Bingham, Hiram, 1875-1956; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938; Jumel, Eliza Bowen, 1775?-1865; Lambert, Samuel W. (Samuel Waldron), 1859-1942; Lambert, Samuel Waldron, 1897-1977; Lewis, Robert, 1862-1939; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1919; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1821, 1862-1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1901-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1930 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1930 Aug-1931 Mar (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1931 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1931 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1931 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1932 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9 - 11)
    - 1932 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1934 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Personal papers
    - Wedding anniversary pamphlet, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bills and receipts, 1879-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Autograph book, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings
    - "Alcohol and Old Age", 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Myths and Memories of Three Score and Ten", [1929?] (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Medical Alcohol", 1930 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Annotated article, "The Present and Future Organization of Medicine", 1932 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Eighteenth Amendment", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Solution of the Prohibition Question", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "What the 18th Amendment has done for the country" and other papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Printed matter
    - Association Against the Prohibition Amendment: pamphlets and bibliography, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Other prohibition related pamphlets and clippings, 1923,1928-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Cigarette News, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and pamphlets, 1924-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)